What the American government had done in
the war on terror was wrong. It was
illegal, it was immoral, it was
unethical, and it was anti-American.
Because if I had not told them that the
CIA was torturing its prisoners, the
American people would never have had any
idea what the government was doing in
their name.
Always tell the truth
because the truth always comes out.
>> [music]
>> I'm joined now by former CIA officer who
led CIA counterterrorism operations in
Pakistan after 9/11 and also was the one
who blew the whistle on the CIA's
torture program during the war on terror
in 2007, John Kiriakou. Thanks so much
for joining us.
>> My pleasure. Good to be with you.
>> Of course. Let's just start out because,
you know, when I was telling people my
age that I'm interviewing you, they were
more excited than when I told them I was
having Justin Trudeau on my show or, you
know, for whatever reason,
uh you know, I'm assuming it's because
of your qualifications and because of
your ability to tell stories, um but
your name has just become, you know,
it's skyrocketing in terms of
popularity. Why is it that so many
people know the name John Kiriakou?
>> It It's crazy, isn't it? And And it's
been like this for about 3 months like
really at this level for about 3 months
now. It's funny, the way it worked out
was was just uh by happenstance. I gave
an interview in January um
to uh
to
Diary of a CEO
podcast and um
and it was a it was a good interview. I
was proud of it. It was a It was an
in-depth interview and um
and uh
after it was done and released a few
days later,
uh a young man from the University of
Texas
took it and chopped it into shorts and
put the shorts out there, but
he gave me an Alvin and the Chipmunks
voice, he slowed my voice down, he had
lasers shooting out of my eyes,
and then released these shorts onto
TikTok and it just
exploded and took on a life of its own.
And I have to say,
it's all been in in good fun.
>> Yeah, and a lot of people, at least my
kind of interpretation of being a spy or
being like an intelligence officer,
their interpretation of it comes from
Hollywood kind of portrayals and comes
from movies and TV shows. So, I'm kind
of curious and I'm sure a lot of people
watching are if you could just kind of
take us through that process of being
recruited as a spy and then kind of once
you're recruited, the training that you
have to kind of undergo. Cuz again, a
lot of people when they kind of are
interpreting what a spy does, they only
see what's happening in the kind of
movie versions of it.
>> Yeah, that's a that's a big question.
So, the way I was recruited is not legal
anymore. I was sort of plucked out of
graduate school by
my grad school adviser who was a CIA
officer undercover as a grad school
adviser. Now, it's it's far less sexy.
You have to go to the CIA website and
and click apply now and just go to the
through the process or
you have to
um approach a CIA recruiter at a at a
job fair, which is also quite common.
Uh once you get in and it's a long
arduous process. Once you get in, you
start the training. Now, it depends of
course
if you're in the Directorate of
Intelligence, which is the analytical
arm, if you're in the Directorate of
Operations, which is out there actually
recruiting spies to steal secrets, maybe
you're in administration, which is
you know, they're the ones that make the
trains run on time, the accountants, the
logistics people,
or the Directorate of Science and
Technology, which is the scientists, the
the forgers, the disguise makers.
Excuse me. People like that. For I
started off in the Directorate of
Intelligence and went through all of the
writing training. And then after 7 and
1/2 years decided that I wanted to do
something completely different. And I
made what at the time was a very unusual
move over to counterterrorism
operations. And so I because I I had
already spent half my career in the CIA.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
I didn't have to go through all the
introductory stuff with what we used to
call CIA 101.
>> Right.
>> And instead I went directly into
you know,
defensive driving, then counterterrorist
driving, and then the uh it was called
uh the operations course accelerated
which teaches you how
how to do the step-by-step of recruiting
spies, steal secrets.
>> And for people who don't know, you kind
of originally are, you know, gaining
your popularity from blowing the whistle
as I said in the introduction on the
torture program. Um it was classified
information, but you have said
repeatedly in interviews that you've
done that you would do it again because
you felt it was almost your duty to do.
Um I'm curious though kind of what
happened like after you revealed that
information, you were in prison. What is
that like being in prison as a spy? I
mean, did you have extra layers of kind
of protection compared to other people?
It would be kind of again an enduring
environment.
>> I'll tell you the truth, the only
threats that I ever faced in prison were
from the guards, not from other
prisoners. It was the guards that were
corrupt and violent. Um
They
It It's kind of a It's kind of a story.
I actually wrote a book about it called
Doing Time Like a Spy: How the CIA
Taught Me to Survive and Thrive in
Prison. And um
>> [laughter]
>> I decided
the day that I arrived that I was going
to use my CIA training to keep myself
safe and at the top of the social heap
and I I started that by forging
strategic alliances.
>> Mhm.
>> On my very first day
uh two
Aryans, neo-Nazis, walked into my cell
and I
I put up my fists, said, "What do you
want?"
They [snorts] wanted a kind
dozen
or
and uh because I was a child molester or
a rat, they told me I could sit with the
Aryans.
But much more importantly
one of the Italians took it upon himself
when he saw in the New York Times that I
was arriving in 4 days, took it upon
himself to go to literally every one of
the Italians and say there's a CIA guy
coming here. He's not an FBI agent. The
FBI are rats and cops and the CIA
[clears throat] protected us from the
terrorists.
And so the Italians welcomed me with
open arms. I made a point
to not respect racial divisions
in prison. Going to prison is like going
back into
1950s America.
All the blacks sit together, all the
Hispanics sit together, all the whites
sit together. Um and and never the two
shall meet. And I didn't respect that.
So I had friends among the blacks, among
the Hispanics, among the Asians.
Um and um it worked out for me. Like I
said, the only real challenge I had was
dealing with the guards and the
administration.
>> And I mean I would imagine that if
you're speaking out against the CIA in
the way that you are now, your former
colleagues within the CIA probably have,
you know, some problems with that. Not
even just the people at the top, but
some of, you know, the people who you
worked probably closely with. Um I'm
curious
>> You be
You'd be surprised, actually. Yeah, my
detractors
were at the top in the CIA and to a man,
they're all either dead or retired. And
there's this new generation of CIA
officers now, and I hear from people a
lot who are inside the CIA telling me
that everything has flipped
and that
the rank and file in the CIA
are supporters of mine,
>> Mhm.
>> not supporters of the torture regime.
Mhm.
>> And I want to kind of help people
understand because you were for a good
part of your career on the ground in
Pakistan, you know, kind of Was it
recruiting? You were doing
counterintelligence, right? Kind of
getting um a whole a hold of information
basically in order to help the United
States during um obviously post-9/11 and
such as well. Um I'm curious though what
the process is like when you're on the
ground in an adversarial country and,
you know, you're trying to recruit, you
know, information and assets when you
have, you know, people who could simply
turn around and go and tell the
Pakistani authorities.
>> Yes.
Yeah, that's that's literally the
challenge that you face every day. It's
very, very difficult. First, what you
want to do is to cultivate strong
liaison relationships, not just with the
host country,
but with other countries represented
there uh that also have coinciding
interests. Uh for example,
you know, Al-Qaeda is an Arab was an
Arab group, and so you want to
have good relations with the other Arab
countries who have embassies in
Islamabad and work together when doing
these counterterrorism raids. The very
first thing that I did when I arrived in
Pakistan
was to come up with a standard operating
procedure to take down a terrorist safe
house. And then I went to uh the FBI,
which was on the lower floor in the
embassy, and um
and coordinated with them, and then I
went over to the Pakistani intelligence
service, the ISI, to say, "I'm the new
guy. I'm here to work with you. This is
what my plan is. And within 48 hours, we
received our first tip where I was able
to go
uh
with the Pakistanis and the FBI,
literally knock down the door of a safe
house with a battering ram, and grab our
very first two Al-Qaeda prisoners. They
happened to be 19 years old. Both of
them burst into tears. One of them asked
if he could call his mom, which I said,
"No, of course you can't call your mom."
And then we just kind of took it from
there. We got to the point where we were
doing
two raids a week, three raids a week,
sometimes two in a night, and then the
night that we that we captured Ayman
al-Zawahiri and many dozens of other
Al-Qaeda fighters, we did 14
simultaneous raids.
>> And going back to kind of my my previous
question there, how are you like
actively tracking in these situations,
whether or not I mean, obviously in more
of a direct sense, your life is at risk,
but even when you were, you know, in the
United States or in countries that
weren't as adversarial, tracking if
you're being, you know, surveilled or
tracking if there's people kind of on
your tail?
>> It's a good question. It's all a part of
the training, all of it. So, before
9/11, I had undergone
all of my operational training, and then
I was asked to return to headquarters
for for 6 weeks for a specialized course
called Advanced Counterterrorism
Operations. This is well before a year
and a half before 9/11.
And um I was one of only 14 officers
worldwide chosen for this class because
we were sort of moving up quickly in
counterterrorism. And so, that included
everything from weapons and explosives
training to advanced counterterrorism
driving, to desert driving,
um to technical courses, you know, bugs
and cameras and
satellites and drones and all kinds of
things like that. And then it just so
happened that 18 months later 9/11
hit
and we were ready to deploy immediately
to the field.
But you have to you have to take
surveillance and counter-surveillance
very, very seriously as well. You have
to always always be on the lookout for
for somebody following you, which
unfortunately happens.
>> Is there ever a sense now that when
you're speaking out about this that you
have a fear that you know, one day
somebody might not be happy that you're
talking as much as you are and revealing
as many secrets if you will as you are?
>> You know what? Why I I used to worry
about that. And then I thought
there's a greater good here and the
greater good will only be accomplished
if I continue to speak out and if I can
inspire other people to speak out. I
believed firmly, I believed in my heart
that what the American government had
done in the war on terror was wrong. It
was illegal, it was immoral, it was
unethical, and it was anti-American.
It may have made us feel good in the
short term, but it set us back over the
long term.
And I decided that I had to keep talking
about it because if if the policy was
going to be changed, I had to be the one
to change it. And then in the end
in December of 2014
the Senate torture report was released.
And Senator John McCain stood up on the
floor of the Senate and said that the
American people owed me a debt of
gratitude because if I had not told them
that the CIA was torturing its
prisoners, the American people would
never have had any idea what the
government was doing in their name.
And then with passage of the
McCain-Feinstein Amendment, torture was
officially banned in the United States
and I'm very proud to have played a role
in that.
>> Is there a sense because obviously there
is a desire for information and for
intelligence and it's more so problems
with how the CIA and the American
government more broadly were going about
getting this information in the way of
that program. Where is the line do you
think in terms of, you know, the need
for information versus still maintaining
a sense of humanity in getting that
intelligence?
>> I'm one of those people who believes
that
I would rather face another attack than
give up my constitutional rights.
>> Right.
>> If we're going to be the good guys,
then we have to be the good guys.
And there's a price that comes with
being the good guys. Look, if if you're
for torture,
then you can be for torture, but you
have to change the law.
The FBI
has been
conducting interrogations since 1945.
They're very good at it. And the way
they do it is they simply build a
rapport, they build a relationship with
the subject, right? They don't beat him,
they don't torture him, they don't they
don't put tubes in his rectum and pump
hummus up in there.
They treat him with respect. They offer
him a cup of tea and apple.
>> that before about hummus. Is that
actually true? They act like
>> Oh, yeah. It's been documented in the
Senate torture report as a form of
torture, unauthorized form of torture,
that was used only to humiliate and to
degrade.
If that's the kind of person that you
want to be, if that's the kind of
country that you want to have,
>> Wow.
>> then change the law. And don't be secret
about it. Just say, "We're going to do
it. We're going to torture."
But otherwise, I believe that we are a
shining city on a hill, a beacon of hope
and light for human rights and civil
rights and civil liberties. So, we're
either going to be the one country or
we're going to be the other country. We
can't be both. We can't tell the world,
"You have to do it this way. You have to
do it that way. You have to respect
human rights when we don't respect human
rights.
>> Right.
>> So, one or the other, but not both.
>> Have you ever because people listening
right now I'm sure are thinking to
themselves, of course he should have
revealed that information. Like that was
information that now as you will
yourself point out has brought kind of
you know light to the situation that was
happening. Um but do you think there's
any world in you know where the
president or the administration
federally in the United States would
consider giving you a pardon of some
kind because of how many people are now
speaking out in support of you?
>> From your lips to God's ears is what I
usually say. I I hope so.
>> Yeah.
>> I I don't know. I I genuinely don't
know, but I hope so.
>> I mean
>> I'm working hard.
>> Obviously you have to make sure.
>> I have asked.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes, I've asked formally. And there are
some very powerful, very important
people who have also asked on my behalf.
>> Mhm.
>> So, I'm I'm hoping for the best.
>> What is that process like? I'm not sure
how much you want to share, but what is
that process like when you're asking for
a pardon, you know, from the US
government?
>> Well, there's the official process and
then there's the unofficial process. The
official process is you go to
the website of the US pardon attorney
and you fill out a form.
The unofficial process is you
lobby
as many people as you possibly can who
are close to the president, personally
close to the president. And you ask them
to sign a letter
asking him specifically to pardon you.
Now,
I've been told that
the president has read the letter.
I've been told that he has been told in
no uncertain uh
no uncertain way that this is something
that these people want, but
they said to me,
"He knows where we stand
but we can't force the man. It could
happen in 6 hours, it could happen in 6
months, it could happen never. Maybe he
doesn't like your face.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I'm I'm just hoping for the best.
>> Um for the average person watching just
to kind of talk a little bit more now
about the realities of the CIA. I've
heard you say before that in order to be
in the CIA, you don't need to be a
sociopath, but you need to have some
form of sociopathic tendencies. Um what
did that look like in kind of a more
like operational day-to-day capacity?
>> Oh, that's an easy one.
Somebody with sociopathic tendencies has
a conscience
reacts on a polygraph exam, but is very
happy to work in legal, moral, and
ethical gray areas
because he or she believes we're the
good guys.
>> Mhm.
>> And so, if I'm instructed to break into
somebody's house and plant bugs
by God, I'll break into the house and
plant bugs or cameras
or do a false flag operation
all because it's good for the United
States.
Uh a normal person wouldn't break into
somebody's house and plant bugs and and
uh
and cameras, but I would.
>> Mhm.
>> That's a sociopathic tendency.
>> And what do you think in terms of if you
know, you're kind of illustrating to
people what the difference was from when
you were operating in the United States
giving kind of you know, information to
the president and such compared to when
you were in places like Pakistan. What
was kind of the difference in the
day-to-day?
>> Oh, there was no comparison.
Um when you're working in Washington at
headquarters and your job, especially in
the Directorate of Intelligence, is to
is to
write papers, articles, briefing bullets
for the president.
There's a certain writing style that
you're highly trained in. You keep it
short and punchy, and you tell the
president, you know,
the fact and the analysis. And that way,
well, you know what? Let me tell you
what the former deputy director of the
CIA used to tell me almost every single
day, like a mantra, he would repeat it.
The job of the CIA is to recruit spies,
to steal secrets, and to analyze those
secrets so that the president can make
the best informed policy.
And that's really what it is. That's the
two different jobs. Recruiting spies,
steal secrets, and then analyzing the
secrets so that the president can make
the best policy. Now, of course, there's
a lot more, there are a lot more moving
parts,
but when it comes right down to its
basics, that's really what it is.
>> And what was kind of like if you were
kind of comparing say post-9/11, the
days after 9/11, compared to, you know,
a more normal time? Like, what was the
difference in terms of the relationship
that people in the CIA had with the
president? Obviously, he gets the daily
brief, the presidential daily brief, but
how, you know, was that different? And
is there ever points where, you know,
I'm sure there are, you kind of, you
know, break in and tell him that this is
urgent information, you need to hear
this right away.
>> That's a tough one. Um,
the relationship with the president
became even closer than it had been. I
mean, the relationship between the
president and the CIA is always going to
be close. Most presidents
make CIA director a cabinet position.
Not all, but most.
And, um, so the relationship is
automatically close.
Depending on who's president, the
president's going to be briefed 6 days a
week.
And also depending on who the president
happens to be,
many of many of those days the CIA
director is going to be in on the
briefing as well as well. So, there's
there's a very, very close
camaraderie between the president and
the uh CIA director. And add in the
National Security Advisor and in many
cases the Vice President as well.
Well, after 9/11, the president
kind of did a deep dive. So, it wasn't
just the CIA director and deputy
director that are briefing the president
and and the and the daily briefer. It's
the head of counterintelligence, the
deputy head of counterintelligence, I'm
sorry, counterterrorism, the deputy head
of counterterrorism, the the deputy
director of counterterrorism for
operations, the Osama bin Laden unit,
the the DDO, you know, this guy, that
guy. There was a parade of people
going over to the White House every day
every day.
And then you had a vice president who
was even more
hands-on than the president was. And
then the vice president is saying, you
know,
"Kill everybody."
>> Right.
>> There's kind of a famous quote made by
Cofer Black, who was my boss at the
Counterterrorism Center, saying that
when he finished with Osama bin Laden,
there would be flies on his eyeballs.
He meant it.
He meant it. And he told the president
and the vice president that that we
would not stop until there were flies on
the eyeballs of Osama bin Laden. And
that set the tone for the response to
9/11.
>> And so, whether it be kind of like after
9/11 or whether it be even recently with
President Trump when he captured and the
United States captured uh Ali Khamenei,
like what is the extent of the resources
that the CIA, you know, will go to to
try and capture some of these targets?
>> Well, they they killed Ali Khamenei uh
in a rocket attack. But, um
the extent is literally to do anything
to
to accomplish the mission.
Whether it's snatching President Maduro
or killing uh Ayatollah Khamenei
or
or, you know, literally it's whatever
the president tells you to do.
You have to You have to carry it out.
Now, post 9/11
what the CIA began doing is borrowing
special forces, uh Navy SEALs, Delta
Force, Army Rangers, um and seconding
them to the CIA because the CIA really
didn't have that kind of expertise.
Not, you know, bear crawling for 3/4 of
a mile and, you know, doing these
practically inhuman things in training.
So, we borrowed special forces.
They were under CIA command, but then at
the end of the operation they would go
back to the Pentagon.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah. And what do you think in terms of
just like cuz I think people are hearing
that and they're getting a sense that
obviously the CIA has endless resources,
they can do practically whatever is
necessary. How does that compare to cuz
I've seen you say before that the CIA
obviously does collect and surveil
Americans as well. Um how does that
compare to what they do to get
information or obtain things about
Americans domestically?
>> See, this is This is one of those issues
that's
that's still sort of in the shadows. It
is patently illegal
for the CIA to collect information on
American citizens or to surveil American
citizens.
>> Mhm.
>> That is supposed to be done exclusively
by the FBI. But we know, thanks to Ed
Snowden,
uh and and other whistleblowers, that
NSA does it as well.
I believe the CIA does it as well.
Um
you know, the problem here is
really a lack of congressional
oversight.
Ever since 9/11 and the um
the amended Executive Order 12333, which
initially had banned the CIA
assassinations,
um
12333 in the aftermath of 9/11 allowed
CIA assassinations and then finally
under the Obama administration allowed
CIA assassinations of American citizens.
Anwar al-Awlaki was alleged to have been
a spokesman for al-Qaeda. Anwar
al-Awlaki was never charged with a
crime. He was an American citizen born
in the United States. He was born in
Albuquerque, New Mexico. Never been
charged with a crime. Never formally
accused of a crime. Never faced his
accusers in a court of law. Never judged
by a jury of his peers. And we
assassinated him.
>> Right.
>> And then 7 days later, we assassinated
his 16-year-old son and his 16-year-old
nephew just because.
And that's illegal.
You can't do that.
>> Is there any sense of like because
obviously all of the information or at
least most of it is classified that
people within the agency or at least
those at the top just don't really care
if they're doing anything remorseful
because they know they have the
classification to protect them?
>> Yeah, I think that's a an important part
of it. Another part is that everybody at
the CIA really has convinced themselves
that they're the good guys.
And that the ends justify the means. And
if taking somebody out, whether legal or
not, is going to
protect or save American lives, then by
God, they're going to do it. And they
convince themselves that they're, you
know, that they're doing their patriotic
duty.
>> Um I wanted to quickly switch before we
finish off into a couple foreign policy
questions because obviously the United
States and Israel, specifically with
Benjamin Netanyahu and Donald Trump, um
despite the recent kind of reporting
that there was that kind of very tense
phone call between the two of them, um
there's been a very strong relationship
historically between the United States
and Israel. And obviously you saw that
with the United States again taking out
Ali Khamenei, the Ayatollah. A lot of
people have always been saying Joe Kent
even for example the ex-counterterrorism
director that a lot of that was you know
in part because of Israel's kind of
calling for the United States to do
that. I wonder from your perspective
just what you know as a CIA former
officer as it relates to the
relationship between the United States
and Israel and how that might kind of
justify and kind of help explain some of
what we've seen recently.
>> I think that the closeness between the
United States and Israel right now is
extraordinarily dangerous for the United
States over the long term.
Listen, whether we like it or not,
whether we like to admit it or not,
Israel is an outcast nation around the
world.
It is not a signatory to the IAEA
convention. It is not a signatory to the
International Criminal Court or the
International Court of Justice. It It
just doesn't believe that it needs to
follow international law.
And so it does anything it wants. And
more often than not Israel's actions are
not in the um
in the best interest of the United
States. I'm confident that Benjamin
Netanyahu convinced Donald Trump that
the Iranian government was a house of
cards. And as soon as the first missiles
flew, the Iranian government would
collapse and that was just simply not
true.
It was Netanyahu who testified before
Congress that as soon as we took out
Saddam Hussein, there would be peace in
the Middle East. As soon as we took out
Muammar Gaddafi, there would be peace in
the Iranians, there would be peace in
the Middle East. Nothing that he tells
us is true. Nothing.
And now we've got Americans coming home
in body bags and for what?
For Israel's foreign policy?
There's no upside for the United States
being involved in this war.
None.
And if Israel wanted to wage war against
Iran, then Israel should have waged war
against Iran. It shouldn't have been up
to the United States to do Benjamin
Netanyahu's dirty work for him.
>> And I've seen you talk as well about
some of the tactics that the Israelis
would use even just throughout your time
as a CIA officer in terms of trying to
turn Americans against their country.
Maybe if you just want to tell you kind
of walk people through um what that
process was like and then I think people
might kind of put some of the pieces
together relative to what's happening
right now.
>> Sure. Israel actively spies on the
United States.
Excuse me.
The United States does not spy on
Israel. We are not permitted to do that.
We have not done that in many many many
decades. But Israel actively spies on
the United States. It has undercover
Mossad and Shin Bet agents spread all
around the country, mostly in American
defense contractors, stealing secrets to
pass back to Israel. Now, we give the
Israelis
98% of what we have.
And they're out there trying to steal
that last 2%.
>> Mhm.
>> So, in my view, at least from a
counterintelligence perspective, Israel
was a hostile country. It remains a
hostile country.
And there's this disconnect between
intelligence
and Capitol Hill
where you've got members of Congress
wearing IDF uniforms on the floor of the
house. You have members of Congress,
including serious senators, like Senator
Tom Cotton, the chairman of the of the
Senate Intelligence Committee, that have
Israeli flags outside of their their
offices. Lindsey Graham, Ted Cruz,
flying Israeli flags. Well, where is
your loyalty?
Is your loyalty to the United States or
is it to this foreign nation? Because it
can't be to both.
>> Yeah. And on that topic, do you think
because of obviously what Israel and the
United States, their partnership is,
Iran starting to become more like
motivated to have some type or at least
their proxy groups or some kind of
attack on American homeland? Are you
worried about that?
>> I'm not. That was another lie
perpetuated by Benjamin Netanyahu. Um in
in the day, you know, the day before,
the day of, the day after the attack on
on Iran, Netanyahu um
made very serious allegations that there
were Iranian terrorist cells in cities
all across the United States.
And that was made up out of whole cloth.
It was a bald-faced lie.
No such cells existed. No such cells
ever existed. He did it just to try to
propagandize the American people and to
sway them into supporting this illegal
attack on Iran.
>> In terms of just before we finish up cuz
I want to ask you too about Jeffrey
Epstein and you've talked a lot about
that. You've said that you think he was
a spy. You said he you in another
interview, I think it was the Diary of a
CEO one that you thought he was an
access agent um potentially for the
Israelis even. Um but I wonder like does
that mean that that whatever government
it was that he was presumably a spy for
could have been involved in perpetrating
the very serious crimes that he
committed?
>> It's entirely possible. And I think it
it comes down to really the the basic,
which is the source of his money.
We don't have any idea the source of his
money. Was it a foreign government? Was
it Les Wexner? Was it the Rothschild
family? We don't know. He never
explained. Investigators were never able
to find out. But uh it it's certainly
possible that a foreign government set
him up,
you know, in in a life of luxury so that
he could serve as an access agent for
them.
It also could be that he kind of stepped
into that once he became wealthy. We're
we'll never know. We'll never know what
the truth was.
>> On the topic of uh the president uh in
the United States and his numerous
assassination attempts, but the primary
one, the one of the first ones in
Butler, Pennsylvania, a lot of people I
think are wondering like what's happened
to that. We haven't heard a lot of
information about that. Is there like a
sense right now that, you know, more
information around that is not a good
thing, or why is it that we haven't
heard more from your perspective?
>> Oh. Oh, I know I I've long been a
supporter for for, you know, complete
and open investigations. I think not
just,
you know, the American people today
deserve an explanation of what happened
in Butler that day, but I think
for history,
historians, future generations deserve
to know what happened that day.
It it it The facts as we know them
just don't make sense. Unless Unless the
Unless we accept the notion that the
Secret Service is just a collection of
incompetent boobs, and I don't think
that they are.
So, how can this 18-year-old kid
get a free shot
at the president of the United States
when others when when Secret Service
agents
saw him on the roof,
saw him preparing to fire.
Uh how How did he get inside the event?
How did he get on to the roof? You know,
what were the circumstances of his
planning?
Why wasn't he shot before he got the
shot off?
Questions that we're just never we're
never going to know the answers to.
And I think that's unacceptable.
>> And like to that end, because it was
similar, obviously Charlie Kirk isn't a
government official, but he was a very
public-facing figure. He had millions of
followers, and similarly, I mean, part
of it I guess with him was the nature of
how he did his events. They were on
campuses, there were thousands of
students there, and they were outside
like I kind of I think a recipe for
disaster in some ways, but you have a
number of conspiracies circulating
around his assassination as well, and
how someone could get that close to him.
Uh
Is there any kind of and what do you
think when you hear some of the
conspiracies that are coming relative to
Charlie Kirk's death?
>> You know, I've said in interviews that I
am the least conspiracy-oriented person
that I know. I really am.
With that said,
there have been conspiracies over the
last conspiracy theories over the last
6, 8, 10 years that have actually proven
to be true.
>> Mhm.
>> The COVID lab leak springs to mind, for
example. Where you you were a crazy
person if you believed it was a lab
leak. And then, lo and behold, it turned
out to be a lab leak.
Um Jeffrey Epstein, another one.
And so, I've gotten to the point where
I believe we should not make any
judgments until all the facts are out.
Of course, this this guy who's the
alleged shooter was caught. He allegedly
confessed to his friends. He allegedly
confessed to his dad.
But there just It seems like there just
has to be more to it. Like it's
impossible to break down that gun so
quickly, for example. How did he get off
get out scot-free?
There just so many questions for which
we don't have answers yet. I think that
I think we need to wait before we make a
decision on whether or not this was a
conspiracy, whether or not perhaps a
foreign government was involved.
We need to wait until
all the information is out there.
>> And on my last
>> That said,
>> Yeah.
>> I I sorry to interrupt you. I I'd like
to know
why in the world the FBI is involved in
this case.
>> Yeah.
>> Because the alleged shooter
left his home in Utah
to go to northern Utah
to shoot Charlie Kirk
in Utah.
He drove back to his home in Utah, told
his friends in Utah. There's literally
no federal aspect to this to this crime
at all. None.
>> Mhm.
>> This should be This should be an
investigation headed by
the Utah State Police and the Utah
Attorney General's Office. So, why in
the world is the FBI involved?
Unless they know something that we don't
know.
And if that's the case, they need to
come out with it.
>> Is there too like a sense right now
because you have like all of the whether
it be Donald Trump's assassination
attempts or whether it be the
assassination of Charlie Kirk looking
back, you know, the attempted
assassinations on the congressional
baseball game, Steve Scalise and all
those people, Gabby Giffords. There's so
many threats towards people right now in
office and yet it seems anytime one of
these threats and one of these like
attempts takes place, it just gets moved
beyond very quickly. Like it gets thrown
aside. In the case of Donald Trump, they
went right into the RNC. They weren't
really talking about it very much at
least from a perspective of concern
afterwards. Is there not a sense that
like we should maybe back up a little
bit and talk about how this is
happening, why this is happening, maybe
bringing down the polarization a little
bit. What's your thoughts on that?
>> See, and that's the key right there.
I've been in Washington for 44 years. It
has become a hideous, angry, ugly,
backstabbing
uh
city. It's nothing like it was when I
first arrived in Washington where
where as soon as the work day was over,
you know, members of opposing parties on
Capitol Hill put their differences
aside. They shared group houses
together. They went to church together.
They played poker together on on
Friday nights.
Those days are gone.
>> Yeah.
>> Where there's there's like active hatred
and disgust of one another and nothing
gets done. And the country just becomes
more and more and more polarized.
>> And just lastly before we finish up, I
want to ask you my final question about
kind of the confidence or optimism you
might have despite all of the kind of,
you know, doom and gloom and negative
things as talking about.
In the sense that it's can feel very
easy I think based off of the way that
the world is going all of the conflicts
all of the tension
to have kind of a feeling as if nothing
will ever get better or nothing will
ever be improved but I hope that people
who have listened to your story over the
course of this interview can you know
feel a sense that they can speak out
what's kind of your I guess just final
message to people in terms of the way
that things are going and how to remain
optimistic despite all of the negatives.
>> Oh this is going to sound simplistic but
it's but it's not always tell the truth
because the truth always comes out
sometimes it takes a while sometimes it
takes years but the truth always comes
out and you're going to want to be on
the right side of it.
>> All right we will leave it there John
Kiriakou thank you so much.
>> My pleasure good to talk to you.
>> Thanks so much for watching if you're
interested in seeing more interviews
focused on the Gen Z perspective make
sure to subscribe and click the
notification bell.